Mss.B.C81.1
American Philosophical Society
José Francisco Correia da Serra papers, 1772-1827
Mss.B.C81.1
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet 200 items
Circa 200 items, mostly transcripts and photocopies of letters; seven mss. letters (formerly B C81.2-8).
Transcripts and photocopies of Correia de Serra correspondence, made by Richard B. Davis for "The Abbé Correa in America," APS Transactions 45, 2 (1955). Seven mss. letters are also included.
Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848
Cooper, Thomas, 1759-1839
Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
Corrêa da Serra, Edward J.
Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
Linnaeus, Carl
Madison, James, 1751-1836
Monroe, James, 1758-1831
Muhlenberg, Gotthilf Henrich Ernst, 1753-1815
Ord, George, 1781-1866
Rawle, William, 1759-1836
Rush, Richard
Skipwith, Fulwar, 1765-1839
Smith, James Edward, Sir, 1759-1828
Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
Walsh, Robert, 1784-1859
Wistar, Caspar, 1761-1818
Box 1
Biographical/Historical note
José Francisco Correia da Serra (1750–1823, APS 1812) was an abbot, diplomat, scholar and botanist. In his work as a botanist he was particularly concerned with the systematic classification of vegetable species. Thomas Jefferson described him as “profoundly learned in several branches of science he was so above all others in that of Botany; in which he preferred an amalgamation of the methods of Linnaeus [1707-1778, APS 1769] and of Jussieu [1686-1758] to either of them exclusively.” Correia spent many years of his life in France, England and the United States where he made the acquaintance of leading European and American intellectual leaders of the time.
Correia was born in Serpa, Portugal, to the physician and lawyer Luis Dias Correia and Francisca Luisa da Serra. In 1756 the family was forced to leave Portugal because the elder Correia’s scientific work had incurred the displeasure of the Holy Office. They settled in Naples, Italy, where the boy came under the tutelage of the abbé and university professor of “Commerce and mechanics” Antonio Genovesi (1712-1769), a major force in the Neapolitan Enlightenment. During this time Correia was also taught in natural history by the botanist Luis Antonio Verney (1713-1792). In 1772 Correia moved to Rome where he studied at the University and other institutions. By that time he was already corresponding with Carl Linnaeus, in Latin. He also made the acquaintance of Don John Carlos of Braganza, second Duke of Lafoens, a member of the Portuguese royal family. The Duke became Correia’s friend and patron.
In 1775 Correia was ordained a Presbyterian abbot; two years later he received the degree of Doctor of Laws. However, it was clear that Correia’s real interest was natural history, especially botany, and that he did not plan to pursue a life in the church. In fact, some of his biographers have suggested that he focused on ecclesiastical studies mainly in order to protect himself in his scientific work from potential suspicions by the Inquisition. Whatever the case, in early 1778 the young abbé, with encouragement from the duke, who hoped to encourage scientific research in Portugal, moved to Lisbon. There he turned his attention to scholarly pursuits and diplomacy.
Correia and the duke set out right away to organize the Royal Academy of Sciences of Lisbon, a learned institution that was dedicated to the advancement of science. Correia also conducted botanical research. He spent the period from 1786 to about 1788 outside of Portugal, and while his activities during this period remain unclear, there is evidence that he visited Rome. In the mid-1790s, after his return to his native country, he began the task of editing what would be the first three of five volumes of Colleccao de livros ineditos da historia Portugueza, an extensive collection of documents.
In 1795 political difficulties compelled Correia to leave Portugal. The Royal Academy and many of its members were viewed with suspicion by certain ecclesiastical groups, especially after Correia befriended the French naturalist and Girondist Peter Marie Auguste Broussonet (1761-1807), who had taken refuge in Portugal. Armed with letters of introduction to several British scientists, Correia traveled to London. He soon became the protégé of Sir Joseph Banks (1743-1820, APS 1787), president of the Royal Society, who facilitated Correia’s election to the Society. He also was welcomed by James Edward Smith (1759-1828, APS 1796), president of the Linnean Society. By then, Correia was already publishing on various natural science topics, especially botany, which contributed to his growing reputation as a naturalist.
For about one year during his residence in London, Correia also served as Secretary to the Portuguese embassy. However, tensions with the conservative Minister compelled him to depart from England in 1802. In the summer of that year, Correia moved to Paris. There he made the acquaintance of leading scientists and other public figures. The list includes Pierre Samuel Du Pont de Nemours (1739–1817, APS 1800), the Marquis de Lafayette (1757-1834, APS 1781), Alexander von Humboldt (1769-1859, APS 1804), the French naturalist Georges Cuvier (1769-1832), Augustin Pyrame de Candolle (1778-1841, APS 1841), and André Thouin (1746-1824), superintendent of the Jardin du Roi, now known as Jardin des Plantes, in Paris. Correia also met Esther Delavigne, who eventually became his lover.
Of particular importance to Correia was his extensive correspondence with friends in Portugal that he maintained throughout his time in London, Paris and then the United States. Through his contact with them he hoped to bring the latest scientific ideas and discoveries to his mother country. His letters are filled with news of new vaccines, maritime maps, instruments, and anything else that he thought might serve to aid the progress of Portugal. Correia’s wide-ranging contacts with fellow botanists made him an important intermediary in the exchanges between naturalists in different parts of the world. In 1807 his own government recognized his contributions by making him a Knight of the Order of Christ.
Overall, Correia’s time in Paris was happy and fruitful. However, life as a liberal under Napoleon was not easy, and Correia soon began to explore the possibility of relocating once again, this time to the United States. Finally, in the winter of 1811, the abbé was aboard the U.S.S. Constitution, on his way to what would become a particularly interesting period in his life.
Correia arrived in Washington, D. C., in early 1812, and he did not lose time in making the acquaintance of leading Americans, including President James Madison. He was anxious to visit Thomas Jefferson but owing to the fact that Philadelphia was the intellectual center of the new nation, he decided to establish himself there first. His European friends had already announced Correia’s imminent arrival to several prominent Philadelphians, including the physicians Benjamin Rush (1745-1813, APS 1768) and Caspar Wistar (1761-1818, APS 1787), and John Vaughan (1756–1841, APS 1784), the treasurer and librarian of the American Philosophical Society. The abbé was elected a member of the Society in January of 1812, before his arrival in the city. He became close friends with Vaughan who soon handled his business affairs and advised him in all kinds of matters. Correia also got to know the botanist Henry Muhlenberg (1753-1815, APS 1785), who introduced him to the physician and botanist Jacob Bigelow (1787-1879, APS 1818). And he reconnected with several Philadelphians he knew from his time in Paris, including the lawyer and financier Nicholas Biddle (1786-1844, APS 1813), and William Short (1759-1849, APS 1804), Jefferson’s private secretary in Paris. Life in Philadelphia was clearly enjoyable for the Portuguese exile but he remained anxious to visit “the great the truly great Mr. Jefferson.” In July of 1813 he left for Virginia for the first of what would eventually be seven visits over a period of about eight years.
Jefferson had been introduced to Correia in glowing letters from Lafayette, Du Pont, Thouin, and Humboldt. It is not surprising, then, that Jefferson received the visitor with warmth and great expectations. They were not disappointed. Jefferson described his guest as “the best digest of science in books, men, and things that I have ever met with; and with these the most amiable and engaging character.” The room in which Correia stayed during his visits to Monticello, the North Square Room, is still known as the Abbé’s room. Correia spent much of his time in Virginia on rambles through the country, often in the company of Thomas Mann Randolph (1768-1828, APS 1794). His interest in natural history eventually also took him to Kentucky, Georgia and north to the Canadian border.
Through Jefferson, Correia made the acquaintance of Francis Walker Gilmer (1790-1826), a promising young man who readily accepted the abbé’s invitation to accompany him on his excursions. In 1816 President Madison asked the two men to deliver a letter from him to the agent of the Cherokee, in the southeastern United States. In the course of their journey through South Carolina and Georgia, they made extensive botanical notations, and Gilmer also recorded several pages of Cherokee vocabulary.
In 1816 Correia received news of his appointment as Portuguese minister-plenipotentiary at Washington, D. C. His expectation that this post would not interfere with his scientific pursuits turned out to be mistaken, even though he never spent more than half a year in the nation’s capital. From the start he was forced to deal with complaints about privateers flying foreign flags who were threatening the Portuguese colonies in South America. The fear was that these privateers, many of whom were American, could encourage and aid a rebellion in Brazil. Correia successfully lobbied the U. S. government for a Neutrality Act that was designed to curb these actions.
In the late 1810s, increasing worries about the turn of Portuguese-American affairs and serious health problems gradually made the abbé’s temper shorter and his spirits lower. He also ultimately became a severe critic of America and Americans, an attitude that contributed to his estrangement from some of his older American friends. However, he also found comfort in new relationships with, for example, the English-born chemist and lawyer Thomas Cooper (1759-1839, APS 1802). Most significantly, Edward Joseph, his fifteen-year old son with his lover Esther Delavigne arrived in the United States from Paris in 1818. Edward, who stayed with his father until their return to Europe, got to know many of his Philadelphia friends quite well. In 1820 father and son sailed from the United States for Portugal via London, a year after Correia had learned of his appointment as Counselor of State for Brazil. Correia spent the last three years of his life in Lisbon, “covered with honors,” as his son Edward wrote in a letter to John Vaughan. He died in Lisbon in 1823.
Correia published many essays and reports on botany in the leading European and American scientific journals of his time. His research centered on the systematic classification of vegetable species. In his work he attempted to apply the methods of compared anatomy of zoology to botany; he sought to group plants into families based on their similarities. His concept of symmetry was later adopted and developed by Candolle. While Correia was not “a member of every philosophical society in the world,” as his young protégé Gilmer wrote enthusiastically in a letter to his brother, he did belong to numerous learned societies. They included the Royal Society, the Linnean Society, the Academy of Science of Paris, and the Société Philomatique. He also offered several courses in botany at the American Philosophical Society.
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists primarily of letters and essays on matters related to botany as well as Correia’s role as Minister Plenipotentiary to the United States. They were written between 1772 and 1827. Also included are several letters and notes by Richard Beale and other persons about Davis’s research on Correia, dated 1949 to 1957. The collection includes a typed table of contents (1958).
The largest single group of letters (25) was written by Correa to John Quincy Adams between 1817 and 1820, when Correia served as Minister Plenipotentiary. They concern official business, including the appointment of various officials and, most prominently, the persistent troubles with American privateers and Correia’s efforts to get the American government to do something about it. Other noteworthy items dealing with official business include a letter by Correia to James Monroe in which he protests a number of assaults by American privateers on Portuguese vessels (1816), and several letters to Secretary of State Richard Rush in which Correia expresses his displeasure about the support given by American citizens to “rebels” in the Portuguese colony of Pernambuco (1817). A letter by Rush to Madison testifies to Correia’s persistence; Rush writes that among the foreign ministers, “the Abbe Correa was the one with whom my official relations were the least smooth” (1817). Correa, in turn, complained to John Quincy Adams in 1819 that “during more than two years, I have been obliged by my duty to oppose the systematic and organized depredations daily committed on the property of Portuguese subjects.” Of interest is also a letter to the Count of Palmela in which Correia assesses the policies of various colonial governments in the West Indies (1820).
Another significant body of letters is addressed to James Edward Smith, a botanist and founder of the Linnean Society in London. The letters, which are dated between 1795 and 1821, deal primarily with botanical matters, including news about fellow botanists, such as Antoine Laurent de Jussieu (1800). The letters are friendly and frequently also include personal news. The letter of September 1801 deals with Correia’s troubles in Portugal.
The collection includes several letters by Correia to Thomas Jefferson. They are friendly letters that reflect their shared interests in the natural sciences. In one letter, for example, Correia writes about his pleasure of sending notes on Captain Lewis’s papers to Jefferson (1816), and another one describes Correia’s intention of visiting Monticello (1818). There is also an undated list of books forwarded to Jefferson.
Items that reflect Correia’s interest in the natural sciences generally, and botany specifically, include three letters by Correia to Carl Linnaeus when Correia was still a student in Rome (1772, 1773, 1774). Written in Latin, the letters deal with botanical topics. A letter to Joseph Banks, written while Correia resided in Philadelphia, refers to seeds and papers that Correia had sent to London (1803), and an undated note in French confirms Correia’s dinner appointment with Alexander von Humboldt.
Several letters shed light on Correia’s interest in and affection for the United States. A letter to Fulwar Skipwith refers to Correia’s idea of living in America as “the utmost of my wishes” and his belief that only an official invitation by the government would make this possible (1808). There is also a letter of introduction for Correia by J. Dauxion Lavaysse, addressed to Benjamin Rush (1811), and a letter of introduction for Robert M. Patterson by Correia, addressed to Smith (1811). A letter written in 1814 refers to Correia’s difficulty of sending money to Paris during Jefferson’s embargo. Also of note is a letter to President Madison in which Correia offers suggestions on how the United States could take advantage of its mineral resources as well as lands as sources of revenue (1814). Correia comments extensively on the “new faculty” of the University of Pennsylvania in a letter to William Rawle (1816). A letter of condolence to Elizabeth Mifflin Wistar speaks to his friendship with the Philadelphia physician Caspar Wistar (1818). The collection also includes an obituary of C. Wistar written by Correia (1818).
Letters written by individuals other then Correia include one by Joseph Banks (1810, in French), and a letter by Joseph Rademaker, Consul general of Portugal, to Secretary of State James Monroe (1816?). There is a group of letters exchanged between Thomas Cooper and Thomas Jefferson which deal with the University of Virginia, including matters relating to the faculty and Cooper’s efforts to secure minerals and works of art (1817-1819). One letter from John Vaughan to Jefferson suggests Landeren Vanapan, who had been recommended by Correia, for a position at the university (1821), and another one by Jefferson to Robert Walsh declines Walsh’s request for material on Jefferson’s life, due primarily to Jefferson’s advanced age and poor health (1823). A friendly letter by Jefferson to Walsh mentions Correia as well as a book on skepticism that Jefferson had recently read (1818). There are also five letters by Henry Muhlenberg to Stephen Elliott, dealing with botanical matters (1812, 1813, 1814). Finally, a particularly heartfelt letter by Francis W. Gilmer informs Dabney Carr of Correia’s departure from the United States in 1820.
Also included in the collection are essays by Correia on several topics, including the “Natural Family of the Aurantia” (1799), the Doryantes (1800), botany (in Latin, undated), “The case of the Brazilian Indian,” and “A description of great English houses and gardens.” There are also reports that Correia prepared for the APS, and there is a dedication to several individuals, including Correia, that was included in Thomas Nuttall’s Journal of the Travels (1821).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Richard Beale Davis and accessioned, 1958 (1958 1046).
Existence and Location of Originals note
Location of originals note in item description, if known.
Early American History Note
This manuscript collection falls outside the geographic scope of the Early American guide (British North America and the United States before 1840). It may be of interest to scholars interested in global history, international relations, imperialism, or the U.S. in the world.
Beyond Early America; Natural history.
- Papers
  - Letter to Carolus Linnaeus, March 28, 1772; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    Scope and Contents note
    Rome, Typed L. 1p. Copy. In Latin. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...)
  - Letter to Carolus Linnaeus, Sept. 15, 1773; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    Rome, Typed L. 4p. Copy. In Latin. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Concerning botany.
  - Letter to Carolus Linnaeus, Jan. 22, 1774; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    (?). Typed L. 2p. In Latin. Copy. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Concerning botany.
  - Letter to [Sir James E. Smith], June 15, 1795; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    London, Typed L. 2p. Copy. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Sir] J[ames] E. Smith, Jan. 30, 1797; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    London, Typed L. 3p. Copy. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Concerning various items of natural history and philosophy. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Sir] James Edward Smith, Norwich, March 23, 1797; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    London, Typed.L. 4p. Copy. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Has the Lisbon academy diploma for him and can get their publications,as J.Banks has. Botanical news.
  - On two Genera of...Aurantia, July 2, 1799; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    read Typescript. 17p. (see Correa de Serra. Letters.. .) Printed: Linnean society of London. Trans., v.5, 218.
  - Letter to [Sir James E. Smith?], July 26, 1800; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    London, Typed L. 3p. Copy. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Botanical news. Friendly letter. Refers to Mr. de Souza.
  - Letter to [Sir James Edward] Smith, Sept. 3, 1800; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    London, Typed L. 2p. Copy. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Botanical news. Will forward parcel.
  - On the Doryanthes..., Dec. 2, 1800; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    [read] Typescript. 7p. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Printed: Linnean society of London. Trans., v.6, 211.
  - Letter to [Sir James E. Smith], Sept. 15, 1801; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    London, Typed L. 2p. Copy. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Printed in part: Davis. Correa in America... APS Trans.,n.s.,v.45, 1955, p.94.
  - Letter to Sir Joseph Banks, bart., Oct. 7, 1803; 10x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    Paris, Typed L. 1p. Copy. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Forwards papers and seeds.
  - Letter to [Sir] J[ames] E. Smith, Jan. 26, 1807; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    Leeds, Typed L. 6p. Copy. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Identification of a plant mentioned in antiquity.
  - Letter to [Fulwar] Skipwith, Sept. 4, 1808; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    Paris, Photostat of A.L.S. 2p.and add.and end. by Robert Gilmor. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Printed: Davis. Correa in America... APS Trans.,n.s.,45,1955, p.123. From original in Historical society of Pennsylvania.
  - Letter to ----, April 7, 1810; Banks, Joseph, 1743-1820
    Photostat of A.L.S. 2p. In French. (see Correa de Serra. Letters.) Concerning botany. From original in the Gray Herbarium at Harvard University.
  - Letter to [Sir James E. Smith?], Oct. 31, 1811; 11x8-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    Paris, Typed L. 2p. Copy. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Introduces R.M. Patterson.
  - Letter to Benj[amin] Rush, Philadelphia, Dec. 17, 1811; Dauxion Lavaysse, J.-J. (Jean-J.), ca. 1770-1826
    Paris, Photostat of A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Introduces Correa de Serra. From original in Library Company of Philadelphia.
  - Letter to Stephen Elliott, Beaufort, S.C., Oct. 5, 1812; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
    Lancaster, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Botanical news. Refers to Correa de Serra and Michaux. From originals in Arnold Arboretum, Harvard University.
  - Letter to Stephen Elliott, Beaufort, S.C., Nov. 11, 1812; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
    Lancaster, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p.and add., end. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Botanical news. Refers to Lewis's Travels, Z.Collins, and Correa de Serra. From original in Arnold Arboretum, Harvard University.
  - Letter to Augustin Pyrame de Candolle, December 1, 1812; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    General note
    Formerly B C81.5
  - Letter to Stephen Elliott, Beaufort, S.C., Jan. 14, 1813; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
    Lancaster, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Botanical news. Refers to the APS and Z. Collins. From original in Arnold Arboretum, Harvard University.
  - Letter to Augustin Pyrame de Candolle, January 29, 1813
    Formerly B C81.6.
  - Letter to Stephen Elliott, Charleston, May 17, 1813; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
    Lancaster, Photostat of A.L.S. 2p.and add., end. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Botanical news. Concerning Z. Collins. Refers to Correa de Serra. From original in Arnold Arboretum, Harvard University.
  - Letter to Monsieur at ami, June 24, 1813
    Formerly B C81.3.
    In French.
  - Letter to Tho[ma]s Jefferson, June 26, 1813; 11x8-1/2; Carr, Frank
    Charlottesville, Typed L. 1p.with [typed] end.: The specimen sent to Mr. Correa at Philadelphia. Copy. (see Correa de Serra. Letters...) Encloses mineral.
    Not located April 2010.